A Register of the Vladislav Al'bionovich (Vl.)Maevskii Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Speeches and writings, 1912-1971 and undated.
  - "Istoriia svoda zakonov,", undated. (Box-folder 18: 1)
  - "Iubilei prosveshcheniia,", undated. (Folder 18: 2)
  - "Iz nashego proshlogo,", undated. (Folder 18: 3)
  - "Iz nedalekogo proshlogo (pechal'noe piatidesiatiletie),", undated. (Folder 18: 4)
  - "Iz nedavnego proshlogo,", undated. (Folder 18: 5)
  - "Iz proshlogo,", undated. (Folder 18: 6)
    Holograph, includes draft and partial typescript
  - "Iz proshlogo, zhizn' v SShA,", undated. (Folder 18: 7)
  - "Izbranie dukhovenstva,", undated. (Folder 18: 8)
  - "Izbranie episkopa,", undated. (Folder 18: 9)
  - "Izumitel'naia chustvitel'nost',", undated. (Folder 18: 10)
    Typescript, includes Serbian text
  - "K stoletiiu Krymskoi voiny,", undated. (Folder 18: 11)
  - "K vyboram mitropolita,", undated. (Folder 18: 12)
  - "Kak bylo v drevnei Tserkvi (presviterianskii sovet),", undated. (Folder 18: 13)
  - "Kak odevalis' nashi predki?,", undated. (Folder 18: 14)
  - "Kaliki perekhozhie,", undated. (Folder 18: 15)
    Typescript, includes related clipping
  - "Kamer-medkhen imperatritsy,", undated. (Folder 18: 16)
  - "Kanonizatsiia russkikh sviatykh,", undated. (Folder 18: 17)
  - "Kanony, sostav soborov,", undated. (Folder 18: 18)
    Holograph, includes related clipping
  - "Khristiane spasaiutsia v Tserkvi,", undated. (Folder 18: 19)
  - "Khristianin v tserkvi i obshchestve,", undated. (Folder 18: 20)
  - "Khristianskie printsipy vlasti,", undated. (Folder 18: 21)
  - "Khristianskoe verouchenie i chelovecheskoe razvitie,", undated. (Folder 18: 22)
  - "Khristianstvo i demokratiia,", undated. (Folder 18: 23)
  - "Khristianstvo i filosofiia v pervye tri veka,", undated. (Folder 18: 24)
  - "Khristianstvo i sotsializm,", undated. (Folder 18: 25)
  - "Khristos rozhdaetsia, slavite!", undated. (Folder 18: 26)
  - "Khristovo voskresenie,", undated. (Folder 18: 27)
  - "Kievo-pecherskii podvizhnik,", undated. (Folder 18: 28)
  - "Kleveta i klevetnichestvo,", undated. (Folder 18: 29)
  - "Kleveta na Boga,", undated. (Folder 18: 30)
  - "Klir i narod,", undated. (Folder 18: 31)
  - "Klirosnoe chtenie,", undated. (Folder 18: 32)
  - "Kniaz' Golitsyn i arkhimandrit Fotii,", undated. (Folder 18: 33)
  - "Kolenopreklonenie,", undated. (Folder 18: 34)
  - "Krizis russkogo slavianofil'stva,", undated. (Folder 18: 35)
  - "Krovavaia istoricheskaia drama,", undated. (Folder 18: 36)
  - "Kto zhe vyzval Mirovuiu voinu?,", undated. (Folder 18: 37)
    Typescript, includes related clippings and note
  - "Lesa nashi russkie,", undated. (Folder 18: 38)
  - "Literatura i kritika,", undated. (Folder 18: 39)
  - "Liubimyi poet russkoi intelligentsii,", undated. (Folder 18: 40)
  - "Liubov'-est' zhizn',", undated. (Folder 18: 41)
  - "Liubov' k vere predpochtitel'na liubvi k obriadu,", undated. (Box-folder 19: 1)
  - "Lozhnoe khristianstvo,", undated. (Folder 19: 2)
  - "Lukavoe vremia,", undated. (Folder 19: 3)
  - "Maksim Suvorov,", undated. (Folder 19: 4)
  - "Malorossiiskoe kazachestvo,", undated. (Folder 19: 5)
  - "Mech' molitvy v dele blagovestvovaniia,", undated. (Folder 19: 6)
  - "Mir bez Khrista,", undated. (Folder 19: 7)
  - "Mir bez liubvi,", undated. (Folder 19: 8)
  - "Mir v ozhidanii,", undated. (Folder 19: 9)
  - "Mnimaia kompetentnost',", undated. (Folder 19: 10)
  - "Monastyrskii otpust,", undated. (Folder 19: 11)
  - "Mozhet-li byt' gosudarstvo bezreligioznym,", undated. (Folder 19: 12)
  - "Mudrets sviatoi Iustin Filosof,", undated. (Folder 19: 13)
  - "Na rekakh vavilonskikh,", undated. (Folder 19: 14)
  - "Na zare 20-go veka (vysochaishii reskript),", undated. (Folder 19: 15)
  - "Nachinaet veiat' postom,", undated. (Folder 19: 16)
  - "Nadrugatel'stvo nad sviatynei,", undated. (Folder 19: 17)
    Typescript, includes notes
  - "Naedine s uchenikami (uedinenie Khrista s uchenikami),", undated. (Folder 19: 18)
  - "Nakanune Krymskoi voiny,", undated. (Folder 19: 19)
  - "Nashe istoricheskoe proshloe,", undated. (Folder 19: 20)
  - "Nasushchnaia potrebnost',", undated. (Folder 19: 21)
  - "Natsional'nyi element v istoricheskom razvitii khristianstva,", undated. (Folder 19: 22)
  - "Nazrevshaia tserkovnaia reforma,", undated. (Folder 19: 23)
  - "Nedavnee proshloe (intelligentnye khristiane),", undated. (Folder 19: 24)
  - "Nedovol'nye liudi,", undated. (Folder 19: 25)
  - "Neobkhodimost' vosstanovleniia sobornoi zhizni v Tserkvi,", undated. (Folder 19: 26)
  - "Nepravil'nye suzhdeniia o sektantstve,", undated. (Folder 19: 27)
  - "Nepravoslavnoe v 'Pravoslavnoi Rusi',", undated. (Folder 19: 28)
  - "Net, eto ne tak,", undated. (Folder 19: 29)
  - "Net mesta somneniiam,", undated. (Folder 19: 30)
  - "Neverie i vera v Boga,", undated. (Folder 19: 31)
  - "Neverie nashikh sovremennikov,", undated. (Folder 19: 32)
  - "Novoe o starom,", undated. (Folder 19: 33)
  - "Novokhristianstvo, pereotsenka dukhovnykh tsennostei,", undated. (Folder 19: 34)
  - "Novorossiiskii krai,", undated. (Folder 19: 35)
  - "Novovremenskii publitsist,", undated. (Folder 19: 36)
    Typescript, includes notes and background materials
  - "Nravstvennoe razvitie i khristianskaia liubov',", undated. (Folder 19: 37)
  - "Nravstvennyi smysl istoricheskogo podviga,", undated. (Folder 19: 38)
  - "Nuzhny pastyri,", undated. (Folder 19: 39)
  - "O novoi broshiure prot. G. Grabbe,", undated. (Folder 19: 40)
  - "O pochitanii sviatykh ikon,", undated. (Folder 19: 41)
  - "O predanii, kak istochnike very,", undated. (Folder 19: 42)
  - "O sviatom khrame,", undated. (Folder 19: 43)
  - "O tserkovnoi propovedi,", undated. (Folder 19: 44)
  - "Obnovlenie tserkovnoi zhizni,", undated. (Folder 19: 45)
  - "Obshchestvennoe bogosluzhenie,", undated. (Folder 19: 46)
  - "Ocherki iazychestva i khristianstva,", undated. (Folder 19: 47)
  - "Odezhda i vlasy klirikov,", undated. (Folder 19: 48)
  - "Okhota na kabanov,", undated. (Folder 19: 49)
  - "Opasnost' obriada,", undated. (Folder 19: 50)
  - "Oppozitsiia krainikh pravykh,", undated. (Box-folder 20: 1)
  - "Ot pastyrstva begut,", undated. (Folder 20: 2)
  - "Otche nash,", undated. (Folder 20: 3)
  - "Otkuda nam nachat' plakat',", undated. (Folder 20: 4)
  - "Otrechenie obiazyvaet,", undated. (Folder 20: 5)
  - "Otstuplenie rimskoi tserkvi ot pravoslavnoi,", undated. (Folder 20: 6)
  - "Otstuplenie zapadnoi tserkvi ot drevnego pravoslaviia,", undated. (Folder 20: 7)
    Typescript, includes related article and clipping
  - "Otsutstvie religioznogo obrazovaniia v russkom obshchestve,", undated. (Folder 20: 8)
  - "Pamiati prof. N. N. Glubokovskogo,", undated. (Folder 20: 9)
  - "Panegerist konstitutsii,", undated. (Folder 20: 10)
  - "Papstvo,", undated. (Folder 20: 11)
  - "Pashkovtsy (Salonnye sektanty),", undated. (Folder 20: 12)
  - "Pastyri i narod,", undated. (Folder 20: 13)
    Holograph, typescript. Includes draft, related clipping, pamphlet and two articles
  - "Pastyri i pasomye,", undated. (Folder 20: 14)
  - "Pastyrskie sobraniia,", undated. (Folder 20: 15)
  - "Patriarshestvo,", undated. (Folder 20: 16)
  - "Patriotizm i chelovechestvo,", undated. (Folder 20: 17)
  - "Patriotizm i kosmopolitizm,", undated. (Folder 20: 18)
  - "Pereselenie slavian v Rossiiu,", undated. (Folder 20: 19)
    Typescript, includes clipping, and notebook with related notes
  - "Petr Arkad'evich Stolypin,", undated. (Folder 20: 20)
    Typescript, includes related clippings, correspondence, notes, and background materials
  - "Pisatel', chitatel' i kritik,", undated. (Folder 20: 21)
  - "Po tserkovnym voprosam,", undated. (Folder 20: 22)
  - "Poberezh'e Gretsii (Putevye vpechatleniia),", undated. (Folder 20: 23)
  - "Pochemu? Sputannoe spletenie,", undated. (Folder 20: 24)
  - "Pokushenie na imperatora,", undated. (Folder 20: 25)
  - "Politicheskaia akhineiia,", undated. (Folder 20: 26)
  - "Politicheskaia nezrelost' i naivnost' amerikantsev,", undated. (Folder 20: 27)
  - "Poniatie o tserkvi,", undated. (Folder 20: 28)
    Typescript, includes related article
  - "Porfirii Uspenskii,", undated. (Folder 20: 29)
  - "Poslantsy amerikanskogo naroda,", undated. (Folder 20: 30)
  - "Posledovateli i protivniki istiny,", undated. (Folder 20: 31)
  - "Postavlenie pervogo patriarkha v Rossii,", undated. (Folder 20: 32)
  - "Potonuvshii mir,", undated. (Folder 20: 33)
    Holograph, includes related clippings and notes
  - "Potrebnost' schastiia, blazhenstva,", undated. (Folder 20: 34)
  - "Pozhelaniia o tserkovnoi reforme,", undated. (Folder 20: 35)
  - "Pravoslavnyi vostok na russkom sobore,", undated. (Box-folder 21: 1)
  - "Prazdnik Rozhdestva Khristova,", undated. (Folder 21: 2)
  - "Predanie sokhrani,", undated. (Folder 21: 3)
  - "Predatel'stvo (pridvornykh, aristokratii i dvorianstva),", undated. (Folder 21: 4)
    Typescript, includes related clippings and noted
  - "Predrevoliutsionnye gody,", undated. (Folder 21: 5)
  - "Predsobornye dumy,", undated. (Folder 21: 6)
  - "Prepodobnyi Ioann Russkii,", undated. (Folder 21: 7)
  - "Prichina neveriia,", undated. (Folder 21: 8)
  - "Prichiny padeniia Pol'shi,", undated. (Folder 21: 9)
  - "Pridvornye intrigi XVIII veka," untitled. (Folder 21: 10)
  - "Prikhod-tserkov',", undated. (Folder 21: 11)
  - "Priskorbnaia neterpimost',", undated. (Folder 21: 12)
  - "Privet studentam Sv. Tikhonovskoi seminarii,", undated. (Folder 21: 13)
  - "Problema smerti,", undated. (Folder 21: 14)
  - "Proizvol vlastei v Sibiri,", undated. (Folder 21: 15)
  - "Prokliatyi rezhim,", undated. (Folder 21: 16)
  - "Prolog k balkanskoi voine,", undated. (Folder 21: 17)
  - "Promysel Bozhii,", undated. (Folder 21: 18)
  - "Propoved' o tsarstve nebesnom,", undated. (Folder 21: 19)
  - "Prosveshchennyi konservatizm i ulitsa (literaturnaia chernaia sotnia),", undated. (Folder 21: 20)
  - "Put'-istina-zhizn' ...,", undated. (Folder 21: 21)
  - "Put' kul'tury i zhizni,", undated. (Folder 21: 22)
  - "Puti russkoi ikony,", undated. (Folder 21: 23)
  - "Radost' apostolov,", undated. (Folder 21: 24)
  - "Rasprostranenie i sokhranenie khristianstva,", undated. (Folder 21: 25)
  - "Rasputin,", undated. (Folder 21: 26-27)
    Typescript, includes related clippings, drafts, and background materials
  - "Razvitie sobornogo instituta,", undated. (Box-folder 22: 1)
  - "Religiia liubvi,", undated. (Folder 22: 2)
  - "Religioznaia kul'tura,", undated. (Folder 22: 3)
  - "Religioznoe nastroenie imperatora Aleksandra I,", undated. (Folder 22: 4)
  - "Religioznoe nevezhestvo,", undated. (Folder 22: 5)
  - "Revoliutsionnyi ober-prokuror,", undated. (Folder 22: 6)
  - "Rim i Rossiia,", undated. (Folder 22: 7)
  - "Rimskaia provintsiia i imperiia,", undated. (Folder 22: 8)
  - "Rimskaia respublika i imperiia,", undated. (Folder 22: 9)
  - "Rol' zaporozhtsev v gaidamachine,", undated. (Folder 22: 10)
  - "Rossiia, Bolgariia i Balkanskaia voina,", undated. (Folder 22: 11)
  - "Rossiia i SSSR v svete faktov,", undated. (Folder 22: 12)
  - "Rossiia Petra i inostrantsy,", undated. (Folder 22: 13)
  - "Rozhdestvo Bogoroditsy,", undated. (Folder 22: 14)
  - "Rus' brodiachaia i bogomol'naia,", undated. (Folder 22: 15)
  - "Russkaia bogoslovskaia nauka,", undated. (Folder 22: 16)
  - "Russkaia diplomatiia na Balkanakh,", undated. (Folder 22: 17)
    Typescript, includes draft and notes
  - "Russkaia publichnaia biblioteka v Belgrade,", undated. (Folder 22: 18)
  - "Russkaia shirokaia maslenitsa,", undated. (Folder 22: 19)
  - "Russkie biblioteki v zarubezh'i,", undated. (Folder 22: 20)
  - "Russkie bogoiskateli,", undated. (Folder 22: 21)
  - "Russkie konsuly na Balkanakh,", undated. (Folder 22: 22)
    Typescript, includes background materials
  - "Russkie revoliutsionery v Shveitsarii,", undated. (Folder 22: 23)
  - "Russkie v Zagrebe,", undated. (Folder 22: 24)
  - "Russkii katolik,", undated. (Folder 22: 25)
  - "Russkoe dukhovenstvo,", undated. (Folder 22: 26)
  - "S chego nachinat' religioznye dela?,", undated. (Folder 22: 27)
  - "S okhotnikami,", undated. (Folder 22: 28)
  - "Sarovskie torzhestva (Iz vospominanii ochevidtsa),", undated. (Folder 22: 29)
    Typescript, two differing copies
  - "Serbskii patriarch Varnava i konkordat s Rimom,", undated. (Folder 22: 30)
  - "Sestrichestvo velikikh derzhav,", undated. (Folder 22: 31)
  - "Shmemanizatsiia,", undated. (Folder 22: 32)
  - "Sila molitvy,", undated. (Folder 22: 33)
  - "Slaviane,", undated. (Folder 22: 34)
  - "Slovesa lukavstviia,", undated. (Box-folder 23: 1)
  - "Smirenie i gnev,", undated. (Folder 23: 2)
    Holograph. Includes related material
  - "So skrizhalei istorii,", undated. (Folder 23: 3)
  - "So stranits istorii. Mazepa,", undated. (Folder 23: 4)
  - "Sobor,", undated. (Folder 23: 5)
  - "Sobornost' tserkovnogo upravleniia,", undated. (Folder 23: 6)
  - "Sobornost' tserkvi,", undated. (Folder 23: 7)
  - "Sobornost' v tserkovnom upravlenii,", undated. (Folder 23: 8)
  - "Soglasno-li khristianstvo s dukhovnoi prirodoi cheloveka?", undated. (Folder 23: 9)
  - "Soiuz Tserkvi,", undated. (Folder 23: 10)
  - "Sokrovishcha tserkovnykh predanii,", undated. (Folder 23: 11)
  - "Soobrazheniia,", undated. (Folder 23: 12)
  - "Sotsial'noe zlo,", undated. (Folder 23: 13)
  - "Sotsiologicheskie oshibki,", undated. (Folder 23: 14)
  - "Sovershennoe neverie,", undated. (Folder 23: 15)
  - "Sovetizatsiia Pravoslavnoi Tserkvi,", undated. (Folder 23: 16)
  - "Sovremennyia iskusheniia,", undated. (Folder 23: 17)
  - "Spasitel' roda chelovecheskogo,", undated. (Folder 23: 18)
  - "Spor 'ottsov' i 'detei',", undated. (Folder 23: 19)
    Clipping, holograph, typescript. Includes related clipping
  - "Starodavnie vremena (Groznyi tsar' i boiarstvo),", undated. (Folder 23: 20)
  - "Strannaia kniga,", undated. (Folder 23: 21)
  - "Stremlenie k schast'iu,", undated. (Folder 23: 22)
  - "Sushchnost' asketicheskikh podvigov,", undated. (Folder 23: 23)
  - "Sv. Pisanie i politika,", undated. (Folder 23: 24)
  - "Sv. Pisanie i Sv. Predanie,", undated. (Folder 23: 25)
  - "Svet razuma i svet vostoka,", undated. (Folder 23: 26)
  - "Svete tikhii sviatye slavy,", undated. (Folder 23: 27)
  - "Sviatitel' Nikolai,", undated. (Folder 23: 28)
  - "Sviatoi apostol Pavel,", undated. (Folder 23: 29)
  - "Sviatye brat'ia,", undated. (Folder 23: 30)
  - "Sviatyni Novgoroda Velikogo,", undated. (Folder 23: 31)
  - "Sviaz' nravoucheniia s vieroispoviedaniem,", undated. (Folder 23: 32)
  - "Sviazi serbov i russkikh v prosveshchenii,", undated. (Folder 23: 33)
  - "Svoboda bogoslovskoi nauki,", undated. (Folder 23: 34)
  - "Svoboda nauki,", undated. (Folder 23: 35)
  - "Svoim umom, russkimi silami,", undated. (Folder 23: 36)
  - "Syny protivleniia,", undated. (Folder 23: 37)
  - "Taina smerti i vechnosti,", undated. (Folder 23: 38)
  - "Teni proshlogo,", undated. (Folder 23: 39)
  - "Tmutarakanskaia Rus',", undated. (Folder 23: 40)
  - "Tol'ko o pokaianii,", undated. (Folder 23: 41)
  - "Tragediia tolstovskogo bogoiskatel'stva,", undated. (Box-folder 24: 1-2)
    Holograph, typescript. Includes background materials, related articles, and notes
  - "Tri istoricheskikh izdaniia,", undated. (Folder 24: 3)
  - "Trogatel'naia sud'ba,", undated. (Folder 24: 4)
  - "Truzhenik nauki,", undated. (Folder 24: 5)
  - "Tsar' i tserkov' na Rusi,", undated. (Folder 24: 6)
  - "Tsareubiistvo,", undated. (Folder 24: 7)
  - "Tserkov' Afrodity,", undated. (Folder 24: 8)
  - "Tserkov' i deti,", undated. (Folder 24: 9)
  - "Tserkov' i gosudarstvo,", undated. (Folder 24: 10)
  - "Tserkov' i modernism,", undated. (Folder 24: 11)
  - "Tserkov' i politika,", undated. (Folder 24: 12)
  - "Tserkov' i zaprosy intelligentsii,", undated. (Folder 24: 13)
  - "Tserkov' Khristova,", undated. (Box-folder 25: 1)
  - "Tserkov', obshchina i izbranie,", undated. (Folder 25: 2)
  - "Tserkov' zemnaia,", undated. (Folder 25: 3)
  - "Tserkovnaia deistvennost',", undated. (Folder 25: 4)
  - "Tserkovnaia ierarkhiia,", undated. (Folder 25: 5)
  - "Tserkovnoe uchitel'stvo,", undated. (Folder 25: 6)
  - "Tserkovnyi despotism,", undated. (Folder 25: 7)
  - "Tserkovnyi obriad,", undated. (Folder 25: 8)
  - "Tvorchestvo,", undated. (Folder 25: 9)
  - "Uchastie klira i mirian v delakh Tserkvi,", undated. (Folder 25: 10)
  - "Uchitelia dukhovnye, ottsy i pastyri,", undated. (Folder 25: 11)
  - "Uchitel'stvo mirian v tserkvi,", undated. (Folder 25: 12)
  - "Utistsi sa puta,", undated. (Folder 25: 13)
  - "Utopiia 'vechnogo mira',", undated. (Folder 25: 14)
  - "Utrata dukhovnykh tsennostei,", undated. (Folder 25: 15)
  - "Utrata natsional'noi idei,", undated. (Folder 25: 16)
  - "V pamiat' druzei moikh (nedavno skonchavshikhsia: arkhiepiskopa Savvy i B. Kozyrenko),", undated. (Folder 25: 17)
  - "V predverii mirovoi voiny,", undated. (Folder 25: 18)
  - "V razvedke,", undated. (Folder 25: 19)
  - "V starodavnie vremena. Tsaritsa-machekha i tsarevna Sof'ia,", undated. (Folder 25: 20)
  - "V sumerkakh revoliutsii,", undated. (Folder 25: 21)
  - "Vazhnoe i otvetstvennoe sluzhenie,", undated. (Folder 25: 22)
  - "Velikie reformy,", undated. (Folder 25: 23)
  - "Velikie sily gotoviatsia k voine,", undated. (Folder 25: 24)
  - "Velikii pastyr' i 'chernye vorony',", undated. (Folder 25: 25)
    Typescript, includes draft notes
  - "Velikii syn Rossii,", undated. (Folder 25: 26)
  - "Velikoe sobytie,", undated. (Folder 25: 27)
  - "Vera mertvaia,", undated. (Folder 25: 28)
  - "Verkhovenstvo naroda,", undated. (Folder 25: 29)
  - "Vernost' pasomykh pastyriu-dukhovniku,", undated. (Folder 25: 30)
  - "Vizantiiskoe i moskovskoe proshloe,", undated. (Folder 25: 31)
  - "Vol'nodumtsy nachala 20-go veka,", undated. (Folder 25: 32)
  - "Vopros nravstvennoi zhizni,", undated. (Folder 25: 33)
  - "Vopros o deistvennosti kanonov,", undated. (Folder 25: 34)
  - "Voskresenie Khristovo,", undated. (Folder 25: 35)
  - "Vospominaniia moi,", undated. (Folder 25: 36)
    Typescript, includes related clipping, correspondence and notes
  - "Vossoedinenie tserkvei,", undated. (Folder 25: 37)
  - "Vozvyshenie vysokoe-padenie glubokoe,", undated. (Folder 25: 38)
  - "Vragi tserkovnogo mira i obnovleniia,", undated. (Folder 25: 39)
  - "Vremenshchiki v Rossii XVIII veka,", undated. (Folder 25: 40)
  - "Vselenskie sobory,", undated. (Folder 25: 41)
  - "Vstrechi i zhizn' s vladykoi Nikolaem,", undated. (Folder 25: 42)
  - "Vstrechi s korolem,", undated. (Folder 25: 43)
  - "Vtorobrachie dukhovenstva,", undated. (Folder 25: 44)
  - "Vtoroi i tretii Rim,", undated. (Folder 25: 45)
  - "Vzaimootnosheniia Rossii i Serbii,", undated. (Box-folder 26: 1-5)
    Typescript drafts, includes handwritten corrections and notes
  - "Vzaimootnosheniia Rossii i Serbii,", undated. (Box-folder 27: 1-5)
  - "Vzaimootnosheniia Rossii i Serbii,", undated. (Box-folder 28: 1)
  - "Zadachi obshchago shkol'nago obrazovaniia,", undated. (Folder 28: 2)
  - "Zakat Vizantii i vozvyshenie Moskvy,", undated. (Folder 28: 3)
  - "Zamechatel'naia dissertatsiia,", undated. (Folder 28: 4)
  - "Zapadnoe zasil'e,", undated. (Folder 28: 5)
  - "Zarozhdenie khristianstva na Rusi,", undated. (Folder 28: 6)
  - "Zaslugi russkoi tserkvi,", undated. (Folder 28: 7)
  - "Zlo ekumenizma,", undated. (Folder 28: 8)
  - "Znamenie vremeni,", undated. (Folder 28: 9)
  - "Zhatvy mnogo, a delatelei malo,", undated. (Folder 28: 10)
  - "Zhenshchina i sem'ia,", undated. (Folder 28: 11)
  - "Zhenshchina v drevnem Rime,", undated. (Folder 28: 12)
  - "Zhenshchina v drevnosti,", undated. (Folder 28: 13)
  - "Zhertvy tiranicheskogo proizvola,", undated. (Folder 28: 14)
  - "'Zlonamerennyi' pisatel' (kritika Dostoevskogo),", undated. (Folder 28: 15)
    Holograph, typescript, includes related clippings
  - "Znachenie Afona dlia Serbii,", undated. (Folder 28: 16)
  - "Gde samaia vysokaia i sovershennaia liubov'?", 1912. (Folder 28: 17)
    Typescript and clipping
  - "Nemetskoe zasil'e v Rossii,", 1915 and undated. (Folder 28: 18)
  - "Skorbnaia godovshchina,", 1918. (Folder 28: 19)
  - "Dukh evangeliia,", 1947. (Folder 28: 20)
  - "Viera i nevierie,", 1947. (Folder 28: 21)
  - "Znamenatel'nyi iubilei (Imperator Pavel i dykhovenstvo),", 1947. (Folder 28: 22)
  - "Nravstvennoe sokrovishche,", 1948. (Folder 28: 23)
  - "Pir viery,", 1948. (Folder 28: 24)
  - "Poklonimsia Khristu,", 1948. (Folder 28: 25)
  - "V edinenii so Khristom i ego sv. tserkov'iu,", 1948. (Folder 28: 26)
  - "Velikii slavianofil,", 1950. (Folder 28: 27)
    Typescript draft and clipping
  - "Vinovniki Pervoi mirovoi voiny,", 1954. (Folder 28: 28)
  - "Zachem voskres Khristos?", 1954. (Folder 28: 29)
  - "Obshchenie imushchestv u pervykh khristian i kommunizm,", 1955. (Folder 28: 30)
    Printed copy
  - "Kipr i Gretsiia,", 1957. (Folder 28: 31)
    Clipping, holograph, and typescript. Includes related clippings
  - "Sovremennye farisei i saddukei,", 1957. (Folder 28: 32)
  - "Velikaia Serbiia ili Iugoslaviia?,", 1957. (Folder 28: 33)
    Clipping
  - "Moi otvet g-zhe L. Solomakho,", 1958. (Folder 28: 34)
  - "Gitler na Balkanakh,", 1959. (Folder 28: 35)
  - "Mistitsizm pri imp. Aleksandre I,", 1961. (Folder 28: 36)
  - "Navet na tseloe soslovie,", 1961. (Folder 28: 37)
    Typescript, and clipping
  - "Tsar' Ivan groznyi i dukhovenstvo,", 1965. (Folder 28: 38)
  - "Oslablenie pastyrskogo dukha,", 1966. (Folder 28: 39)
  - "Amerikanskoe posol'stvo v Rossii,", 1967. (Folder 28: 40)
  - "Sarovskii podvizhnik,", 1968. (Folder 28: 41)
  - "Pervye vieka khristianstva i sovremennost',", 1969. (Folder 28: 42)
  - "Khristos idet...sriashchite!,", 1970. (Folder 28: 43)
  - "Rozhdestvenskaia elka,", 1970. (Folder 28: 44)
  - "Radost' voskreseniia Khristova,", 1971. (Folder 28: 45)
- Subject file, 1869-1978 and undated. (Box 29)
  Acts, agendas, appeals, articles, brochures, bulletin, circulars, clippings, correspondence, epistles, leaflets, lists, minutes, notes, obituaries, pamphlets, reports, schedules and syllabi, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Aleksander, King of Serbia, 1934-1964 and undated. (Folder 29: 1)
    Clippings
  - Anarchists--Russia, 1964 and undated. (Folder 29: 2)
  - Arkhiepiskopiia pravoslavnykh russkikh tserkvei v zapadnoi Evrope, ekzarkhat vselenskogo patriarkhata
    - General, 1958-1971 and undated. (Folder 29: 3)
      Clippings, notes
    - Liturgical notes for Annunciation celebration, 1950. (Folder 29: 4)
  - Arsen'ev, Nikolai S., 1967-1968. (Folder 29: 5)
  - Athos (Greece).
    See also Oversize file/Athos (Greece), and Speeches and writings/Research notes/Athos (Greece)
    - General, 1927-1970 and undated. (Folder 29: 6)
    - Lists, 1960-1961 and undated. (Folder 29: 7)
      Includes lists of donors, and monks living on Mount Athos
  - Beilis affair, 1963 and undated. (Folder 29: 8)
  - Berdiaev, Nikolai A., 1963-1967 and undated. (Folder 29: 9)
  - Berezov, Rodion, 1951-1963 and undated. (Folder 29: 10)
    Article, clippings
  - Bunin, Ivan A., 1932-1966 and undated. (Folder 29: 11)
  - Canon law, undated. (Folder 29: 12)
    Notes
  - Carpatho-Russia, 1936-1939 and undated. (Folder 29: 13)
  - Catholicism, 1926-1969 and undated. (Folder 29: 14)
    Articles, clippings, notes. Includes materials on the Second Vatican Council
  - Delianich, Ariadna, 1960-1971 and undated (Folder 29: 15)
  - Don Cossacks, 1930-1969 and undated. (Folder 29: 16)
    Clippings, correspondence, notes
  - Dostoevsky, Fedor M., 1952-1973 and undated. (Folder 29: 17)
  - Eastern Catholic Church, 1954 and undated. (Folder 29: 18)
  - Ecumenical movement, 1936-1974 and undated. (Box-folder 30: 1)
    Clippings, notes, reports
  - Gor'kii, Maksim, 1966 and undated. (Folder 30: 2)
  - Grebenshchikov, Georgii Dmitrievich, 1930-1964 and undated. (Folder 30: 3)
    See also Correspondence/Grebenshchikov
  - Holy Trinity Orthodox Monastery, 1957 and undated (Folder 30: 4)
  - Intellectuals--Russia--Political activity--History, 1946-1968 and undated. (Folder 30: 5)